Hey look guys my name is Jenna welcome
back to my siblings boss series so today
we're talking all about virtual
destructors in C++ if you're not sure
what a destructor is and definitely
check out that video first and also you
don't know what a vessel function is
then there's also that video that you
should probably check out because a
virtual destructor as you can imagine is
kind of the combination of both of those
things now this is kind of simple this
video probably shouldn't take too long
and we're just going to dive into an
example and take a look immediately but
essentially virtual disruptors are very
very important for when you're dealing
with polymorphism so in other words if I
have a series of subclasses and all that
inheritance if you guys haven't you guys
don't know what inheritance isn't simple
sports definitely check out that video
as well but if you have a class like a
and then a class babies derive from a
and you want to actually reference Class
B as Class A but it's actually Class B
and then you decide to delete a or it
gets deleted by some kind of way then
you also want the destructor of B to run
not just a and that is essentially what
virtual disruptors are and that's what
that's what they facilitate so that
probably made no sense to you in your
head because it's kind of hard to
visualize how it's going to jump into
some code straight away and and just see
this in action okay so all I'm going to
do here is make two classes one is going
to be called base because this is going
to be our base class I'm just gonna make
a public constructor and I'll just print
out that constructed just so that we
know that the class gets constructed and
and that the constructor gets called
then I also write a destructor
and I'll say destructed okay or actually
I'll just call this constructor and
destructor okay cool I want to do the
exact same thing for another class I'll
just copy and paste it but I'll call
this derived and it's actually going to
be derived from base so we have derived
as a subclass of the base class and then
over here I'm gonna do the exact same
thing and in fact I'm just going to
write which one was constructed so base
constructor based destructor and then
also derived constructor and derived
destructor okay so let's consider two
scenarios here the first thing I want to
do is create
an instance of the base class I'm gonna
allocate this on the hip so that we can
be explicit with our creation and
deletion camp so base base equals new
base and I'll write the elite base and
now I'll just print like a little
divider between the two like that and I
also do derived derived equals new
derived just like that oops right
they'll call it and we'll delete dropped
as well
let's hit f5 and see what happens with
this current setup here so you can see
nothing really is different I mean I
haven't marked anything anything is
virtual at all but I have a base and a
right we're derived is also of the type
base because it's a subclass of the base
class so 0 5 ok so as you can see here I
guess what you probably would expect
would happen happen here when we created
the base class it only called the base
construction destroyed after we deleted
it which is exactly what you would
expect and 4 derived as well what it
seemed to have done was it first called
the base constructor then the derived
constructor and then after we deleted it
it called the derived destructor first
and then the base destructor so
everything is working correctly here as
we would expect now the problem of
needing a virtual destructor arises when
we have this scenario so let's just copy
this one more time but this time what
I'll do is I'll actually have like a
polymorphic kind of type here so else
called poly basically what we're doing
here is we're creating a derived
instance however we're assigning it to a
base type like this so we are treating
this kind of poly object as if it was a
base pointer here but it's actually a
pointer to a derived derived type so in
this case if we run this code and see
what happens you can see that we have
this third scenario here where the base
constructor and derived constructor gets
called correctly just as we adjust as we
would expect from that second example
however when it comes time to delete it
just the base destructor is called not
the derived destructor we're missing
this here and that's very important
because that could cause memory leak and
I'll show you how in a minute but you
can see that what specifically happening
here is when we go to delete poly it
doesn't know that actually this
destructed I'm calling my potentially
have another destructor
because it's not marked as virtual which
means that say boss boss hasn't actually
know that I okay this there might be
like a method and an overwrite some kind
of overridden method in another kind of
class further dive down the hierarchy
because with methods of course we're
just with a normal method if we mark it
as virtual it has the ability to be
overridden which means it has to finish
at the V table and all that has to work
and be set up with distractions it's a
bit different because a virtual
destructor you're not overriding the
destructor you're just adding a
destructor kind of so in other words if
I change the base this base destructive
to be virtual it's actually going to
call both it's gonna end up calling that
derived destructor first and then go up
the hierarchy and also call the base one
we'll see that in a minute so to do this
what we need to do is simply just mark
this or actually first of all let's talk
about the problem why do we even need to
call the derived destructor well
consider this example maybe we had a
member here like an int array or
something that was allocated on the heap
here in the constructor we actually
allocate it like this maybe and then in
the destructor we decide that we need to
delete that array now in this scenario
if we just hit f5 with this current code
what's actually happening over here
because you can see it's not calling
that derived destructor but it is of
course calling the derived constructor
what's obviously happening is that we're
allocating all of this memory 20 bytes
here and then we're never actually
calling this line of code because the
destructors not called so we're never
deleting that heap allocated array which
means that we have a memory leak so how
do we go about solving this well all we
really need to do here is just mark this
base destructor as virtual which means
that there is basically the possibility
for this class to be extended to be
subclassed and we might be including a
destructor that also needs to get called
this basically tell us above us hey you
need to call the derived disruptors if
they're present so now let's hit f5 and
see what we get ok cool check this out
so we have the exact same behavior now
as we did in the second example that
derived a structure is called first and
then the bank's destructor is called
like this which means that this array
does indeed get cleaned up and
everyone's happy even if we do treat it
kind of as the polymorphic type in a
sense that
address it or we treat it like that base
class type anyway I hope you guys enjoy
this video very simple bit of a quick
tip really important whenever you're
writing whenever you're on in class that
you will be extending or that might be
subclass whenever you're basically
permitting a class to be subclassed
you need 200% declare your destructor as
virtual otherwise no one's going to be
able to safely extend that class
including yourself because if you do
that you can't use the destructor
because it will never get called if
you're treating that class by its best
type which might be the case that you're
passing it into a function as well and
maybe that function only takes it as
like a base pointer and then deletes it
or does whatever it does this is have
example anyway so definitely make sure
that you are declaring the destructors
was virtual if you're allowing that sub
classing to actually happen if you liked
this video please hit the like button
you can also help support the series by
going passionate conference - the China
a huge thank you as always to all my
lovely supporters this series wouldn't
be here without you guys I will see you
next time goodbye
[Music]